Guide to the Mary Hunter Wolf Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mary Hunter Wolf papers
1867-1999
YCAL MSS 716
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
51.11
(80 boxes) + 1 broadside.
The papers contain correspondence, writings, financial records, audiovisual material, photographs, printed material, personal papers, scripts, scrapbooks and other material that document Mary Hunter Wolf's career as an actor, director, and theater educator. Correspondence, printed material, project files, and other material document Wolf's work with the Center for Theatre Techniques in Education (CTTE) and other educational theater projects. Also documented are her activities with the American Actors Company, the American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy, the Society of Stage Directors and Choreographers, and other organizations as well as her professional associations with Agnes De Mille, Katherine Dunham, Horton Foote, Jerome Robbins, Andrius Jilinsky and others. Files relating to her direction of stage productions of The Respectful Prostitute, Only the Heart, Out of Dust, Ballet Ballads, Musical Americana, Carib Song, Great to be Alive! and others are also included in the collection. Personal papers include correspondence, greeting cards, photographs, and academic, legal, and financial records.
Wolf, Mary Hunter, 1904-2000
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary Hunter Wolf, 1996-1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 35, 53, 55, 63, 64, 76, 81 (sound and video recordings): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 77 (reel-to-reel tape): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Mary Hunter Wolf (1904-2000)
Mary Hunter Wolf was born in Bakersfield, California in 1904, and moved with her family to Hollywood in 1906. She graduated from Hollywood High School in 1922, and attended Wellesley College before moving to Santa Fe, New Mexico, where she met Lynn Riggs, Sinclair Lewis, and Willa Cather. After developing an early interest in the performing arts she directed pageants at Wellesley and in Santa Fe, and organized a dance concert for the choreographer Agnes De Mille, a Hollywood friend. In 1928, she enrolled in the University of Chicago and became involved in Chicago's Cube Theatre where she directed several productions. Cast as Marge in the radio show Easy Aces in 1931, she moved with the show to New York and remained with the program until it was cancelled in 1945. Over the next thirty years she studied with former members of the Moscow Art Theatre and taught at Tamara Daykarhanova's School for the Stage; established the American Actors Company with Andrius Jilinsky; co-founded the American Theatre Wing Professional School; and directed numerous stage and radio productions in New York (on and off-Broadway), Chicago, Washington, D.C., Dallas, and Westport, Connecticut. Included in her productions were Only the Heart (her Broadway debut in 1944), Carib Song (with Katherine Dunham in 1945), Ballet Ballads (1948) and numerous others. In 1953, she was named executive director of the American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy (ASFTA) in Stratford, Connecticut, and during the next twenty years she worked as the company's associate producer, director of development, and consultant for planning. After working on educational outreach programs for the ASFTA for several years, in 1970 Wolf was named director of educational projects, and founded the Center for Theatre Techniques in Education (CTTE). With the CTTE she developed educational programs that were incorporated into Connecticut public school curriculums. Wolf was active in the Society of Stage Directors and Choreographers in various capacities from 1967 to 1988, and served on several Connecticut arts councils and commissions. Her marriages to John F. Sullivan and Herman Wolf ended in divorce. She retired to Anchorage, Alaska in 1992, and died in Hamden, Connecticut in 2000.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, financial records, audiotapes, photographs, printed material, personal papers, scripts, scrapbooks, and other material that document Mary Hunter Wolf's career as an actor, director, and leader in educational theater. Correspondence, printed material, project files, and other material documents Wolf's work with the Center for Theatre Techniques in Education (CTTE) and other educational theater projects. Also documented are her activities with the American Actors Company, the American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy, the Society of Stage Directors and Choreographers, and other organizations as well as her professional associations with Agnes De Mille, Katherine Dunham, Horton Foote, Jerome Robbins, Andrius Jilinsky and others. Files relating to her direction of stage productions of The Respectful Prostitute, Only the Heart, Out of Dust, Ballet Ballads, Musical Americana, Carib Song, Great to Be Alive! and others are also included in the collection. Personal papers include correspondence, greeting cards, photographs, Hollywood High School and Columbia University records, and legal and financial records.
Arrangement
Organized into six groupings: I. June 1996 Acquisition. II. March 1997 Acquisition. III. December 1997 Acquisition. IV. February 1999 Acquisition. V. March 1999 Acquisition. VI. December 2000 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Educators -- United States; Theater -- Education; Theater -- Production and direction -- United States; Theater -- Study and teaching -- United States; Theater -- United States; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Photographs; Educators -- United States -- 20th Century; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States -- 20th Century; De Mille, Agnes, 1905-1993; Dunham, Katherine, 1909-2006; Foote, Horton, 1916-2009; Jilinsky, Andrius; Robbins, Jerome, 1918-1998; Wolf, Mary Hunter, 1904-2000; American Actors Company; American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy; Center for Theatre Techniques in Education; Stage Directors and Choreographers Foundation
- June 1996 Acquisition, 1867-1996; 1; 46.26 linear feet (69 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This acquisition contains audiotapes, correspondence, financial papers, notes, personal papers, photographs, printed material, scripts, scrapbooks, writings, and ephemera by or relating to Mary Hunter Wolf. Includes files relating to the American Actors Company, The American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy, and the Center for Theatre Techniques in Education (CTTE); audiotapes of interviews with Mary Hunter Wolf and others; and scripts, poetry and biographical material by others.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in order received.
  General note
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 519.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Mary Hunter Wolf.
  - Correspondence, flyers, brochures, clippings, writings, [circa 1944-1986]; 17 (Box 1)
    Includes Hollywood; Girl of the Golden West; The Respectful Prostitute; The Sounding Brass; Shubert Archive; Publication; letters of recommendation; MHW--personal; Israeli Hgh School Conference.
  - Correspondence, flyers, brochures, clippings, writings, [circa 1944-1986]; 11 (Box 2)
    Includes The Respectful Prostitute; Peter Pan; Falk Foundation; O'Keefe investors; It's About Time.
  - Correspondence, flyers, photographs, and projects, [circa 1975-1987]; 19 (Box 3)
    Includes CTTE files; Wilbur Cross High School; CTTE/Conte; Educational Center for the Arts; Area Cooperative Educational Services (Peter Yang); Connecticut Commission on the Arts; CTTE/Area Cooperative Educational Services resumes handicapped gifted; Conte 1983 budget; copies /correspondence 1980; 1983 correspondence (carbons); Gesell Institute/Galland; Dramatech; CTTE Summary for J. Eddy; Project Discover; The Corporation Papers; CTTE Minutes; Theatre Today lecture series--North Haven Library; Museum of the American Theater; The Respectful Prostitute; University of Chicago candidates; Conte Arts Library; Conte Press clippings; Ben Page Theater/Drama creativity.
  - Correspondence, flyers, and projects, 1982-1989, undated; 8 (Box 4)
    Includes CTTE financial statements; CTTE public relations; Conte resource Pact; Mike Nichols article; comprehensive Arts program; Museum of American Theatre; Gifted and Talented --clearinghouse; MHW correspondence.
  - Business and project files, clippings, brochures, correspondence, [circa 1970-1985]; 19 (Box 5)
    Includes City Spirit Artists, Inc.; Arts Connection; Leadership Training Institute (LTI); Title III Book; Ben Page; Foundations Information/Application; Out of My House; Project Histories with funding given to J. Eddy; Sponsor campaign.
  - Business and project files, correspondence, 1951, undated; 6 (Box 6)
    Includes Revue miscellaneous business; investors B file; investors C file; professional dates-material used; CTTE; sample evaluation form.
  - Correspondence, receipts, [circa 1951-1982]; 12 (Box 7)
    Includes Humanities 1978; Final education program; George Wesley Richmond; Current Theatre News; Title III Book-semi final sections; articles; final evaluation Parents Encourage the Gifted; Conte Arts Magnet School.
  - Correspondence, clippings, receipts, 1951-1954; 6 (Box 8)
    Includes Musical Americana
  - Flyers, writings, correspondence, clippings, photographs, [circa 1941-1987]; 18 (Box 9)
    Includes American Actors Company; New Haven Board of Education; New Haven Public Schools; Company general information; special education requests for proposals, handicapped and gifted; State Task Force--gifted and talented; Stratford Public Schools.
  - Flyers and writings, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, receipts, booklets, writings, [circa 1949-1985]; 18 (Box 11)
    Includes The Liar; Mid-Passage --Sundgard; American Actors Company; Art History, Audio-Visual; Mrs. Gibbons Boys, unproduced plays inactive; Christmas lists--1950.
  - Correspondence, receipts, booklets, writings, 1943-1978, undated; 7 (Box 12)
    Includes MCA Incorporation; CTTE current; OUA/DATA's Connecticut Foundation Directory, etc.
  - Writings, correspondence, business papers, booklets, contracts, musical scores, [circa 1943-1984]; 23 (Box 13)
    Includes Wharton Dance; The Tinder Box; Come Back, Little Sheba; Peg O'My Heart; Sundgaard; Bijou addresses; Only the Heart; contracts.
  - Clippings, advertisements, booklets; musical scores; scripts, [circa 1935-1984]; 18 (Box 14)
    Includes Jerome Robbins; Oral--Mystic State Gifted Center; Sartre; Junius Eddy; National Business Consortium gifted and talented.
  - Advertisements, booklets, clippings, correspondence, business papers, folders of scripts, [circa 1930-1992]; 17 (Box 15)
    Includes Answer These; Theater catalogues; Auto; 1983 tax statements; Prudential Bache; Wolf; Title VII; Colloquium--Houston.
  - Correspondence, clippings, scripts, business papers, music scores, [circa 1940-1990]; 16 (Box 16)
    Includes Columbus Project; American Legend -1940; Junius Eddy report; fundraising; extra press clippings.
  - Scripts, writings, correspondence, academic planner; clippings, booklets, [circa 1947-1989]; 23 (Box 17)
    Includes unused material--revue; reading, Compton; Virginia Gordoni; American Shakespeare Festival Theatre--old; Appliances--guarantees, instructions, etc.; Fitelson & Lesky; divorce papers.
  - Photograph and artworks, 1981, undated; 6 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, writings, clippings, programs, flyers, scripts, [circa 1941-1992]; 10 (Box 19)
    Includes Theater information; American Actors Company; Miscellaneous; You Touched Me; William Wolf school file, 1964-1965; Texas.
  - Correspondence, writings, clippings, production programs, flyers, scripts, 1941-1964, undated; 4 (Box 20)
    Includes Missisippi summer project; Far Smiling Land by Andrew Jones; American Actors Company.
  - Correspondence, business papers, scripts, clippings, booklets, [circa 1955-1984]; 12 (Box 21)
    Includes Theatre in education; family and personal; American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy; tax 1964; Rosenbaum; personal correspondence; David Wolf, Louise Wolf, others; Calvin Taylor/Torrance.
  - Booklets, business papers, correspondence; writings; clippings; booklets; scripts, [circa 1948-1992]; 21 (Box 22)
    Includes Barbara Kolb; obituaries; press (urban, rural); Out of Dust; A Musical Play.
  - Scripts, writings, programs, clippings, photographs, correspondence, business papers, booklets, [circa 1947-1992]; 14 (Box 23)
    Includes gifted and talented reimbursement forms; Community Children and Family Services; CTTE copies; MHW.
  - Writings, programs, clippings, correspondence, business papers, 1978-1988, undated; 8 (Box 24)
    Includes CTTE; American Shakespeare Festival Theatre; Paris.
  - Scripts, financial papers and receipts, advertisements, correspondence, clippings, pamplets, photographs, writings, [circa 1941-1972]; 12 (Box 25)
    Includes Ballet Ballads; Carib Song; Respectful Prostitute; Frank Hauser; board meeting; personal correspondence.
  - Scripts, financial papers and receipts, correspondence, clippings, pamplets, writings, 1949-1966, undated; 7 (Box 26)
    Includes 1966 Joseph Verner Reed--ex. file; Webster correspondence; American Shakespeare Festival Theatre act of incorporation; Ballet Ballads; Musical Americana.
  - Clippings, correspondence, business and financial papers, booklets, production programs, [circa 1922-1995]; 22 (Box 27)
    Includes Miscellaneous bills paid 1994; move to Anchorage; miscellaneous newspaper and magazine articles; credit card purchases; MHW correspondence 1994 Jan-Aug; archival information; Hollywood High School year book; Women in Theatre Project.
  - Cards, financial papers; photographs; flyers; clippings, writings, booklets, correspondence, notebook, magazine articles, [circa 1987-1996]; 7 (Box 28)
    Includes Photographs from trip; miscellaneous photographs; The Respectful Prostitute; education; Trotsky; MHW photographs; Christmas and birthday cards, 1994 Dec; tapes MHW/Bradley; Dorothy and Lillian Gish.
  - Correspondence, programs, writings, photographs, clippings, flyers, financial papers, [circa 1991-1993]; 12 (Box 29)
    Includes Biography; European trip, 1971; correspondence 1992-1993; photographs from Brigadoon; press and promo.; photographs from Maytime; contracts and miscellaneous; American Actors Company, Anthropology; Peter Pan; financial papers; American Shakespeare Theatre; financial '87- 91.
  - Photographs, correspondence, writings, clippings, maps, booklets, [circa 1935-1995]; 6 (Box 30)
    Includes Great to be Alive; London and Stratford; MHW photographs; Shape of Things to Come; MHW and friends--photographs; miscellaneous biographical; file--letters answered.
  - Clippings, correspondence, flyers, writings, booklets, programs, photographs, [circa 1941-1996]; 18 (Box 31)
    Includes Foster Parents Plan, Inc.; MHW 1996; Sue Hill; recommendations; Kaiser ships Paramount (Wilk); travels; summer institute; biographical; 1972 Christmas cards; Mary Austin; Tennessee Williams poems, Shuku Iwasaki.
  - Booklets, business papers, clippings, writings, photographs, financial papers, appointment books, calendars, planners, [circa 1952-1994]; 9 (Box 32)
    Includes Biographical; budget; American National Theatre and Academy; Valdez; Bill Wolf; Alaska; New Haven; lists; Henry & Sara; Arts and Humanities High School; consignments; Ballet Ballads.
  - Correspondence, writings, clippings, flyers, booklets, financial papers, scripts, planners, [circa 1990-1995]; 22 (Box 33)
    Includes Landers; Lucy Kroll; Yale; Esther Stinemen; Barbara Smith; Santa Fe; Jerry Robbins; design; Kaiser--notes; Kaiser--correspondence; Carib Song; Only the Heart.
  - Programs, scripts, writings, photographs, correspondence, clippings, business papers, booklets, [circa 1935-1996]; 23 (Box 34)
    Includes CTTE History; Katherine Dunham; DeMille; correspondence-professional; New Haven public schools; Jack Harris Bonham; biographical correspondence--T. Compton; farewell parties; breathing and vocal exercises; Whitney Center; CTTE-Betsy Ross Magnet School; MHW professional; You Touched Me! by Tennessee Williams and Donald Windham--"Taos version."
  - Photographs, correspondence, clippings, programs, business papers, booklets, scripts, [circa 1946-1996]; 28 (Box 35)
    Includes CTTE Workshops; CTTE general correspondence; CTTE Coop High School; Society of State Directors and Choreographers; Nellie Kelly estate; Jilinsky musical notes; Horton Foote; James Farrell; Sharon Esdaile; Shroud My Body Down; Arts Division of Area Cooperative Educational Services; Arts Commission; correspondence, family; workshop file; press; American Theater Wing; books list, correspondence-Iwasaki.
  - Notecards, correspondence, writings, business papers, financial papers; photographs, clippings, booklets, [circa 1941-1993]; 6 (Box 36)
    Includes History of American theater; NBC Television; Gift of Watercolor; MHW biography; James Joyce; notes from T. Wilder; Dallas clippings; The Respectful Prostitute.
  - Scripts, photographs, booklets, planners, diploma, certificates, flyers, programs, correspondence, clippings, financial papers, writings, [circa 1937-1993]; 15 (Box 37)
    Includes Agnes De Mille; old school papers; Call it a Day; radio scripts; play scripts; play directed at Cyrano's Off Center Playhouse, Jerusalem High School American Advisory Board; MHW oral history tape transcriptions; MHW publicity photographs; birthday, 1993; Ballet Ballads.
  - Scripts, planners, memo book, [circa 1938-1994]; 3 (Box 38)
    Includes Carib Song.
  - Clippings, booklets, magazines, business papers, writings, scripts, programs, receipts, financial papers, correspondence, [circa 1992-1994]; 10 (Box 39)
    Includes American Actors Company; expenses and receipts for Only the Heart; draft of book, Joy of Acting by Andrius Jelinsky; experimental theater.
  - Clippings, booklets, college records, maps, diploma, production programs, scripts, [circa 1919-1994]; 10 (Box 40)
    Includes Hollywood High School records; Columbia University records; Henry & Sara.
  - Correspondence, telegrams, clippings, programs, business papers, scripts, drawings and prints, travel log, writings, notebook, [circa 1942-1995]; 7 (Box 41)
    Includes American Actors Company; correspondence--friends; correspondence 1980, etc.; miscellaneous newspaper clippings; travel for Yale.
  - Correspondence, clippings, financial papers, programs, Socialist Party membership card and booklet, music, writings, booklets, [circa 1949-1995]; 14 (Box 42)
    Includes Christmas 1994; Socialist Party; American Actors Company; professional correspondence 1994; friends correspondence 1994; Connecticut Gifted and Talented; family correspondence, 1994; June Degnen 1994; CTTE.
  - Correspondence, financial papers, booklets, notecards, music, address books, notebooks, planners, clippings, [circa 1992-1995]; 18 (Box 43)
    Includes Christmas and addresses; music book; Christmas cards 1995; Christmas mail; letters concerning Ballet Ballads; New Stages etc.; American Shakespeare Theatre; library list of books disposed of in Hartford before coming to Alaska; Yale.
  - Ledgers, notebooks, booklets, periodicals, acting exercises; programs, correspondence, financial papers, photographs, [circa 1937-1989]; 19 (Box 44)
    Includes Photographs--Spain.
  - Journal, printed material, 1941-1987, undated; 3 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence, certificate, clippings, conference booklets, photographs, business and financial papers, scripts, writings, [circa 1937-1996]; 21 (Box 46)
    Includes; Paris Review; T. Williams; Title III book manuscript; Margaret Coate-1981 (CTTE).
  - Correspondence, clippings, booklets, production programs, financial papers, [circa 1926-1996]; 10 (Box 47)
    Includes MHW biography; autographs and letters; Jerry Robbins; Great to be Alive; Press--MHW; personal; publicity clippings; personal clippings; taxes 1992/travel; personal publicity--old; American Actors Company--taxes.
  - Booklets, correspondence, programs, clippings, theater exercises, scripts, [circa 1938-1990]; 5 (Box 48)
    Includes General information on gifted and talented; Israel Arts and Sciences Academy.
  - Planners, interviews, correspondence, scripts, research descriptions, financial papers, writings, [circa 1940-1996]; 6 (Box 49)
    Includes MHW productions; material on Katherine Dunham and Dances of Haiti; Frances Dunham; Hollywood; book publishers; doctoral thesis on Horton Foote by Crystal Lea Brian; MHW interview transcript.
  - Photographs, notebooks, certificate and drawing, [circa 1972-1991]; 14 (Box 50)
  - Photographs, 1990; undated; 12 (Box 51)
  - Photographs, Christmas cards, slides, Puck magazine, passports; audiocassette, [circa 1890-1995]; 23 (Box 52)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Use of original audiotape is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Includes Socialist Party; friends' correspondence; American Actors Company; Governor's inaugural ball, 1948; MHW radio interview, April 1995.
  - New Haven Symphony Orchestra by CPTV with introduction by Walt Monteith, 1986 February 26; YCALMSS716_0001; 1; 01:01:10 (Box 53, Item barcode 39002102370294)
    Use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Interviews, chronology, transcripts, newsletters, flyers, financial and business papers, clippings, correspondence, advertisements, writings, calendars, programs, [circa 1956-1996]; 3 (Box 54)
    Includes "For Patricia Willis"; Alaska newspaper clippings; Only the Heart.
  - Envelope, photographs, medals, negatives, slides; dissertation on Mary Hunter Wolf, [circa 1991-1994]; 10 (Box 55)
  - Family portraits, 1867, undated (Box 56)
    Includes daguerrotype and framed photographs.
  - Family portraits, undated (Box 57)
    Includes daguerrotype, tintype and framed photograph.
  - Certificate, Life magazine, pages of old scrapbook, clippings, programs, [circa 1948-1991]; 2 (Box 58)
  - Box of beads, pocketknife, inscribed ring, belt, envelope containing lock of hair and sash, medal, mirror, metal purse, fabric with lace, miniature axe, wedding book, [circa 1896-1901] (Box 59)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings, periodicals, photographs, programs, [circa 1938-1942] (Box 60)
  - Scrapbook containing newsletter, telegrams, correspondence, clippings, [circa 1948-1949] (Box 61)
  - Two scrapbooks containing flyers, booklet, programs, magazine, clippings; one scrapbook concerns Only the Heart, [circa 1944-1950]; 2 (Box 62)
  - Audiocassettes, [circa 1979-1988]
    Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information
    - Selected Poems 1930-1982 by Peggy Pond Church, Sante Fe, NM, 1 (Box 63, Item barcode 39002099367683)
    - Gato [?] AM..., 1981 June 22; 1 (Box 63, Item barcode 39002099367691)
      Includes notes from taped lectures, Chapel Hill
    - CTTE [board] meeting, 1983 February 4; 1 (Box 63, Item barcode 39002099367709)
    - Theater Tech. 1st program, undated; 1 (Box 63, Item barcode 39002099367717)